I wonder if it's okay to continue
obsessing over physical beauty.
I'm a bit embarrassed
to ask this question.
I go to the gym at least 3 times a week
and I get a massage once a week
I don't wear the same outfit many times.
I go to the gym to look nice and fit,
more than for any health benefits.
Before I met Jungto Society,
I'd see women who don't care
for their looks and think,
'What's wrong with her? I don't get it.'
I thought it was only natural
to maintain one's looks like I do.
But as I learn more from Jungto,
I'm beginning to question my assumptions.
I notice you mention in your Dharma talks,
"Let go of greed towards your body"
and "Let go of your attachment
towards your body".
It now makes sense to me, but in real life
I find many benefits to looking beautiful.
For instance, if I go to the gym
looking cute, the trainer looks
after me 3 or 4 times more.
When I go shopping looking nice,
the salespeople treat me nicely.
When asking for directions looking nice,
people even walk me to my destination.
I'm not causing anyone harm
by looking nice.
I've been coming to Jungto Centre
three times a week,
as I joined the "People of Jungto" program.
I use my spare time to go to the gym
and get facials and massages.
And yet I wonder
if I should abandon my fixation
towards physical appearance.
Honestly speaking, I think many women
prefer to be complimented on
their looks than on their personality.
While I understand your teachings,
I wonder if I need to emotionally
let go of my obsession over beauty.
Well, just live as you are.
(Audience Laughter)
Keeping it up may be tiring,
but if you don't mind the effort, why not?
For example, you'd get up an hour early
when everyone else is asleep,
so that you can put makeup on.
We can't say that's a bad thing, can we?
Makeup may cost you money.
But others spend money on food
and don't mind putting on the weight.
If you'd rather eat less
and spend more on makeup,
why not? It's okay. Do as you like.
Thank you.
You're welcome.
(Audience Laughter)
(Applause)
Who is ultimately happy
when your inner-self is beautiful?
It is yourself, is it not?
Who is ultimately happy
when your outer appearance is beautiful?
It is others, is it not?
You might think you're being altruistic
(Audience Laughter)
by pleasing others with your appearance.
But just know that
when you're pretty on the inside,
you're the one who gets the cake.
You get the cake, others get the crumbs.
When you're pretty on the outside,
others get the cake, you get the crumbs.
All things considered, that's fine too.
But if your obsession
reaches the point of suffering,
if you agonize
over maintaining your physical appearance,
if you feel deprived
because you don't have enough money
for plastic surgery,
or if you feel like
you don't have enough time to balance work,
Dharma talks and gym altogether,
then I'd advise you to give up something
to ease the suffering.
As of now, you claim
you are managing everything pretty well.
You seem to have misunderstood
the Dharma talk to say
desire for physical beauty is a bad thing.
What could be bad
about desiring physical beauty?
You exercise regularly because you want to.
You're not stealing from anyone to do so.
There's nothing bad about it.
But if you become too caught up
with your desire to look beautiful,
you'll feel sad as you grow older.
Then you'll be getting Botox shots
or plastic surgery to remove wrinkles.
You'll be dying your hair
to cover up your grey hair.
If you continue obsessing over your appearance,
you'll feel despair and bitterness
as you grow older and see your body age.
You're still young,
hence it appears like
things always turn out the way
you want them to.
As you continue maintaining your physique,
you need to be able to
let go of your obsession
so that you won't despair in the future.
What if you get into an accident
and break your arm?
Some people wouldn't despair,
whereas those that obsess
over their appearance
may take it as a detrimental thing.
Hence letting go of your obsession over
appearance enables you
to prevent sufferings
that may arise in the future.